Okay, now it's time to talk about how
the relationship between American
Indians and all those colonizing
Europeans changed over time. And it's a
saucy one. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, now the relationship between
Europeans and indigenous Americans at
first first contact was in general
pretty civil. Each side was attempting
to figure out exactly what to do with
the other. But over time, the
relationship got uh complicated and grew
way more complex. Spain, for example,
complicated the relationship by
resorting to brutality and subjugation.
And then indigenous peoples complicated
the relationship when they attacked
colonial settlements like they did for
example in Virginia which ultimately led
to Bacon's rebellion of which I'll have
more to say in the next video. And I'm
not saying here that they were wrong to
try to reclaim land that had been taken
from them forcibly. I'm only saying that
such events complicated the relationship
between European colonists and American
Indians. However, by this period that
we're in, indigenous groups and
Europeans had developed a pretty good
sense of what the other was about. And
both sides began to see the value in
allying with each other against their
common enemies. In fact, during this
period that we're in, all major European
imperial powers allied with American
Indian groups and armed them and used
those alliances to fight each other.
Additionally, sometimes indigenous
groups took advantage of those alliances
in order to achieve their own goals. And
probably the best example of that is the
Beaver Wars, which was an on-again
off-again conflict throughout the 17th
century. Ultimately, the Irakcoy
Confederacy, who were allied with the
British emerged victorious in these
conflicts, which reshaped the power
dynamics in the Great Lakes region.
Additionally, the Irakcoy victory had
the effect of displacing several
indigenous people groups in the area who
then moved south and west. And as it
happened, some of them moved right into
the areas in which colonists happened to
be expanding, which led to frontier
conflicts like we saw in Bacon's
Rebellion. Oh, and by the way, if you
want no guys to follow along with this
video and quizzes to help you remember
everything, then check that link in the
description. As I mentioned in the
previous video, the Beaver Wars were
conflicts over control of the extremely
profitable fur trade in the Great Lakes
and Ohio River Valley region. And so
facing the depletion of beavers in their
territory, the Irakcoy Confederacy
sought to expand into the territory of
neighboring indigenous peoples. And they
figured they had a pretty good shot at
success since the Dutch had been trading
metric buttloadads of guns to the
Irakcoy for a while. Anyway, due to
European alliances on both sides, the
French got pulled into one side of the
conflict while the Dutch and British got
pulled into the other side. And then the
Europeans did the same thing with these
alliances for their own advantage. For
example, in 1702, we got the War of
Succession being waged in Europe. Long
story short, it was a contest over who
would control Spain's kingdom and vast
colonial empire. Now, because much of
Spain's colonial empire was over in the
Americas, the war jumped across the
Atlantic and heated up over there, too.
So, Spain allied with France, and then
both of them fought against the English,
but each side also relied heavily on
their own alliances with indigenous
groups. The point is, though the
relationship was fraught, alliances
formed between Europeans and American
Indians, in which each sought to use the
other for their own advantage. And in
some cases when the rivalries in Europe
spilled over into the colonies,
indigenous groups could sometimes become
pawns in larger conflicts that really
had nothing to do with them. But
alliances aside, there were times in
which the relationship got so bad that
it led to bloodshed. And unfortunately,
I could give you quite a few examples of
this trend, but I'll restrain myself to
give you one, namely Metacom's war. Side
note, you'll also hear this called King
Phillips War, but both are referring to
the same thing. And why would we have
two different names for the same event?
Because never forget, US history hates
you. Anyway, after decades of threats
from New England settlers pushing
further and further west, as was their
custom, the Wampenog, whose land the
British were encroaching upon,
retaliated. Now, a guy named Metacom was
the chieftain of the Wampenog, but the
settlers at Plymouth called him King
Phillip. In fact, earlier in their
relationship with New England settlers,
Metacom and his brother sought peace
with the colonizers by requesting that
English names be given to them. And so,
that's why they called Metacom Phillip.
And I'm not just throwing around this
trivia for poops and giggles. That name
itself gives you some insight into the
progression of the relationship. At
first, the Wampenog tried to coexist
with the colonist. In fact, Metacom
happened to be the son of Massoy, who
had originally helped the Plymouth
colonist avoid starvation in the early
years. But the fact that we're now
talking about King Phillip's war tells
you that things uh changed over time.
Anyway, in order to oppose the British
settlers, Metacom forged an alliance
with other American Indian groups in the
area. And after doing so, Metacom's
forces attacked English settlements all
over the New England region, completely
destroying about a dozen Puritan towns
and killing hundreds of colonists. And
not surprisingly, those city on a hill
New Englanders were in no mood to be
killed by these recalcitrant natives. So
they retaliated and eventually captured
and killed Metacom, which essentially
brought the conflict to an end. And
although this conflict styied colonial
expansion westward for a while, the
amount of death sustained by the
Wampenog and their allies meant that
resisting these white settlers would be
nearly impossible. But sometimes the
difficult nature of this relationship
led to cultural accommodation on the
part of Europeans toward indigenous
folks. And here the best example is the
Pueblo revolt of 1680. Now there was a
whole lot of killing involved in this
conflict. So, it's very much not going
to sound like an example of
accommodation, but just wait till the
end. So, as you may recall, one of the
main Spanish tactics for spreading their
empire and consolidating their power was
by means of the mission system, which is
to say, Catholic missionaries attempted
to convert indigenous peoples to
Christianity. And here in the American
Southwest, Spanish missionaries were
doing their darned best to convert the
native Pueblo, but the Pueblo continued
to practice their indigenous belief
systems to the great annoyance of the
Spanish. Add to that the growing pueblo
resentment against the encomenda system
and the population lost on account of
disease and the Spanish began to think
that these indigenous people were
stubborn and ungrateful for the Spanish
efforts to bring the glories of western
culture to them. Therefore the Spanish
missionaries grew increasingly
heavy-handed about the matter and
finally the pueblo weary of these
foreign efforts to erase their culture
rebelled. Now the rebellion was led by a
medicine man named Pope who preached
that driving out the Spanish and
returning to the traditions of pueblo
culture would usher in the return of
peace and prosperity. And so in a
furious burst of violence, the Pueblo
destroyed all Catholic churches in the
area and killed a bunch of priests and
Spanish settlers and finally drove them
from all Pueblo land. However, about a
decade later, the Spanish, not being
accustomed to having their hind parts
handed to them, returned. And they
launched a brutal campaign against the
Pueblo and killed a bunch of them
because those Pueblo couldn't seem to
understand just how much Spanish Jesus
loved them. Anyway, the Spanish were
successful and reestablished control in
Santa Fe. But now that they were back in
control, it appears that they had
learned a thing or two about how
indigenous people aren't that fond of
being subjugated and having their
culture trampled underfoot. So the
Spanish made some accommodations for the
conquered Pueblo. For example, they
offered land grants to the Pueblo and
appointed a representative to monitor
and uphold Pueblo interest and rights.
Additionally, although the Spanish
priests did return, they were far more
lenient about allowing Pueblo to hold to
their traditional belief systems. Okay,
click here to watch my other videos for
unit 2. And you can click here to grab
my video note guides, which are going to
help you cram all the contents of this
course firmly into your brain folds. I
appreciate you coming around and I'll
catch you on the flip-flop.